<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-09-06T06:04:39+00:00</updated><id>https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Compendium of Suśruta in Time and Space</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Problem of Jejjaṭa</title><link href="https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/the-problem-of-Jejjata/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Problem of Jejjaṭa"/><published>2025-09-05T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-09-05T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/the-problem-of-Jejjata</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/the-problem-of-Jejjata/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="jejjaṭa">Jejjaṭa</h2> <p>Related to the the problem of Candraṭa, we may note that manuscripts containing the “Candraṭa verse” that ends, “… आलोक्य जैज्जटीं ||” have sometimes been misinterpreted as containing a commentary by Jejjaṭa. This is the case, for example, with MS Bikaner Anup 4391, that was reported in this way in NCC <a class="citation" href="#ncc">(<i>New Catalogus Catalogorum, An Alphabetical Register of Sanskrit and Allied Works and Authors</i>, 2015, pp. 7: 317)</a>. This led Meulenbeld to assert the existence of a commentary by Jejjaṭa on the basis of this manuscript <a class="citation" href="#meul-hist">(Meulenbeld, 1999, pp. 1B 506 n.360)</a>. In fact, MS Bikaner Anup 4391 is the text of the <em>Suśrutasaṃhitā</em>, with the Candraṭa verse in the colophon. It is likely that this is the same case for MS London IOLR Taylor 1842: this is currently being investigated.</p> <p>MSS currently known to have the Candraṭa verse:</p> <ul> <li><a href="https://panditproject.org/entity/108211/manuscript">MS Bikaner Anup 4391</a></li> <li><a href="https://www.panditproject.org/entity/108178/manuscript">MS London IOLR Taylor 1842</a></li> <li><a href="https://www.panditproject.org/entity/113349/manuscript">MS Kurukṣetra Jawaharlal Nehru Library 19786</a>, f. 78v</li> </ul> <h3 id="testimonia">Testimonia</h3> <p>There are numerous statements in the secondary literature asserting that commentators cite Jejjaṭa’s commentary on the Suśrutasaṃhitā. For example, the NCC (idem) names Hemādri, Vijayarakṣita, Ṭoḍarānanda, Nāganātha, and Rūpanayana, to which Meulenbeld adds Ḍalhaṇa, Gayadāsa and Niścalakara (ibid, v. 1A, p. 385). Some of these may indeed be concrete evidence for a commentary on the Suśrutasaṃhitā by Jejjaṭa. They need to be studied individually, especially those of Ḍalhaṇa and Niścalakara. However, those that I have examined from Indu on the <em>Aṣṭāṅgahsaṅgraha</em> (missing reference), are from Jejjaṭa on the <em>Carakasaṃhitā</em>, not the <em>Suśrutasaṃhitā</em>.</p> <p>At the time of writing, the fact that Ḍalhaṇa and others apparently cite Jejjaṭa while writing on the <em>Suśrutasaṃhitā</em> makes it likely that there was once a commentary by Jejjaṭa on that text. However, the commentary is lost and the manuscripts that have been cited as containing parts of the commentary do not do so.</p> <h2 id="references">References</h2> <ol class="bibliography"><li><div class="row"> <div id="meul-hist" class="col-sm-10"> <div class="title"><em>A History of Indian Medical Literature</em></div> <div class="author"> Gerrit Jan Meulenbeld </div> <div class="periodical"> 1999 </div> <div class="periodical"> </div> <div class="links"> </div> </div> </div> </li> <li><div class="row"> <div id="ncc" class="col-sm-10"> <div class="title"><em>New Catalogus Catalogorum, An Alphabetical Register of Sanskrit and Allied Works and Authors</em></div> <div class="author"> V. Raghavan, K. Kunjunni Raja, C. S. Sundaram, and <span class="more-authors" title="click to view 5 more authors" onclick=" var element=$(this); element.attr('title', ''); var more_authors_text=element.text() == '5 more authors' ? 'N. Veezhinathan, N. Gangadharan, E. R. Rama Bai, Siniruddha Dash, others' : '5 more authors'; var cursorPosition=0; var textAdder=setInterval(function(){ element.html(more_authors_text.substring(0, cursorPosition + 1)); if (++cursorPosition == more_authors_text.length){ clearInterval(textAdder); } }, '10'); ">5 more authors</span> </div> <div class="periodical"> 2015 </div> <div class="periodical"> </div> <div class="links"> <a href="https://vmlt.in/ncc/" class="btn btn-sm z-depth-0" role="button">URL</a> </div> </div> </div> </li></ol>]]></content><author><name>Dominik Wujastyk</name></author><category term="commentators"/><category term="Candraṭa"/><category term="Jejjaṭa"/><category term="manuscripts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Did he write a commentary?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Problem of Candraṭa</title><link href="https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/the-problem-of-Candrata/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Problem of Candraṭa"/><published>2025-09-03T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-09-03T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/the-problem-of-Candrata</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/the-problem-of-Candrata/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="candraṭa">Candraṭa</h1> <p>Almost exactly a year ago, in a <a href="https://sushrutaproject.org/2024/09/12/candrata/">blog post of 12 September 2024</a>, we wrote about several manuscripts of the <em>Suśrutasaṃhitā</em> that end with the verse,</p> <blockquote> <table> <tbody> <tr> <td>सौश्रुते चंद्रटेनेह भिषक्टीसटसूनुना</td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>पाठशुद्धिः कृता तन्त्रे टीकाम् आलोक्य जैज्जटीं</td> <td> </td> </tr> </tbody> </table> </blockquote> <blockquote> <p>The correction of readings (pāṭhaśuddhi) in the treatise of Suśruta was done by Candraṭa the son of the doctor Tīsaṭa, after studying the commentary of Jejjaṭa.</p> </blockquote> <p>Eggeling, for example, characterised a manuscript with this statement as follows <a class="citation" href="#egge-1887">(Eggeling et al., 1896, p. 928a)</a>:</p> <blockquote> <p>“Portions of the <em>Sauśrutīya Āyurvedaśāstra</em> in Candraṭa’s revision of the text made after Jaijjaṭa’s (Jaiyyaṭa’s) commentary. Whether the explanatory notes added above and below the text belong to Jaijjaṭa’s commentary does not appear”</p> </blockquote> <p>Some scholars have suggested that this verse describes an actual commentary or independent work of text-criticism by Candraṭa called the <em>Suśrutapāṭhaśuddhi</em> <a class="citation" href="#meul-hist">(Meulenbeld, 1999, pp. 2A: 123)</a>.</p> <p>We are beginning the work of examining the MSS that apparently transmit Candraṭa’s this work, but the suspicion is growing that in fact Candraṭa did not write a <em>separate work</em> with this title. Rather, he produced a <em>version</em> of the <em>Suśrutasaṃhitā</em> that specifically adherसौश्रुते चंद्रटेनेह ed to the opinions of the commentator Jejjaṭa. The manuscripts we are seeing with the verse cited above are the <em>Suśrutasaṃhitā</em>, not some commentary on it.</p> <p>This would cast Candraṭa as a scholar who produced a new version of the whole Suśrutasaṃhitā, one that specifically accepted the readings of the earlier commentator Jejjaṭa.</p> <p>The commentator Ḍalhaṇa does not mention Candraṭa’s name anywhere in his extensive commentary. He is elsewhere not shy about citing predecessors, so we deduce that he was not aware of Candraṭa’s work.</p> <p>At present, this is a hypothesis, and our project members are discussing the issue and thinking of ways to test the hypothesis.</p> <h2 id="references">References</h2> <ol class="bibliography"><li><div class="row"> <div id="egge-1887" class="col-sm-10"> <div class="title"><em>Catalogue of the Sanskrit Manuscripts in the Library of the India Office. Part V. A.: Scientific and Technical Literature</em></div> <div class="author"> Julius Eggeling, Ernst Windisch, Ernst Anton Max Haas, and <span class="more-authors" title="click to view 2 more authors" onclick=" var element=$(this); element.attr('title', ''); var more_authors_text=element.text() == '2 more authors' ? 'Arthur Berriedale Keith, Frederick William Thomas' : '2 more authors'; var cursorPosition=0; var textAdder=setInterval(function(){ element.html(more_authors_text.substring(0, cursorPosition + 1)); if (++cursorPosition == more_authors_text.length){ clearInterval(textAdder); } }, '10'); ">2 more authors</span> </div> <div class="periodical"> 1896 </div> <div class="periodical"> </div> <div class="links"> <a href="http://n2t.net/ark:/13960/s2kbk5zcrg9" class="btn btn-sm z-depth-0" role="button">URL</a> </div> </div> </div> </li> <li><div class="row"> <div id="meul-hist" class="col-sm-10"> <div class="title"><em>A History of Indian Medical Literature</em></div> <div class="author"> Gerrit Jan Meulenbeld </div> <div class="periodical"> 1999 </div> <div class="periodical"> </div> <div class="links"> </div> </div> </div> </li></ol>]]></content><author><name>Dominik Wujastyk</name></author><category term="commentators"/><category term="Candraṭa"/><category term="manuscripts"/><category term="Jejjaṭa"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Did he write a commentary?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Social Importance of Variant Readings</title><link href="https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/social-importance-of-variant-readings/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Social Importance of Variant Readings"/><published>2025-08-20T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-20T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/social-importance-of-variant-readings</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/social-importance-of-variant-readings/"><![CDATA[<p>The great Sanskrit scholar Yādavaśarman Trivikrama Ācārya edited three editions of <em>The Compendium of Suśruta</em> (<em>Suśrutasaṃhitā</em>) <a class="citation" href="#chak-2018a">(Chakraborty, 2018)</a>. They were published in 1915, 1931 and 1938 <a class="citation" href="#susr-1915">(Ācārya, 1915; Ācārya, 1931; Ācārya &amp; Ācārya, 1938)</a>. These editions, including the manuscripts Ācārya used, were discussed by Wujastyk et al. <a class="citation" href="#wuja-2023">(<i>On the Plastic Surgery of the Ears and Nose. The Nepalese Version of the Suśrutasaṃhitā</i>, 2023, chap. 3)</a>.</p> <p>The Suśruta Project has been using an etext transcription of the 1938 edition, typed and generously made public by Tsutomu Yamashita and Yasutaka Muroya in 2014. Because of the limited availability of text editions in Japan at the time, this etext used the 1931 edition for the sūtrasthāna and śārīrasthāna parts of the text. The Suśruta Project 2.0 is currently inputting these parts from the 1938 edition, so that the etext will represent the 1938 edition in a unified way.</p> <p>A side-effect of this work means that we have gained the ability to compare the changes that Ācārya made to these parts of the work between his 1931 and 1938 editions. As an example, <a href="https://saktumiva.org/wiki/wujastyk/susrutasamhita/03-su.sa/03-za-vulgate-1931?upama_ver=i4l46viq17">here is the 1931 edition of the <em>Compendium</em> with the apparatus showing the changes that Ācārya made to the śārīrasthāna for his 1938 edition</a>.</p> <h2 id="when-should-i-get-married">When should I get married?</h2> <p>If you scroll to passage 10.53 in the śārīrasthāna, where the care of children is being described, you will find a statement advising a young man of 25 years about whom to marry. In the 1915 and 1931 editions, the passage reads :</p> <blockquote> <p>अथास्मै पञ्चविंशतिवर्षाय द्वादशवर्षां पत्नीमावहेत्पित्र्यधर्मार्थकामप्रजाः प्राप्स्यतीति॥</p> <p>Then, a man of twenty-five should take a wife of twelve so that he may obtain children for the sake of ancestral duty, wealth, and pleasure.</p> <p>— Suśrutasaṃhitā Śārīrasthāna 10.53 <a class="citation" href="#susr-1931">(Ācārya, 1931, p. 337)</a></p> </blockquote> <p>But in the 1938 edition, Ācārya emended the passage to read “a wife of sixteen.” Viewed as an important social injunction, this is a major change.</p> <p>In his footnote on this change <a class="citation" href="#susr-1938">(Ācārya &amp; Ācārya, 1938, p. 392)</a>, Ācārya noted that on this point he was adopting the reading of the “palm leaf manuscript” (<em>षोडशवर्षां इति ता। पुस्तके पठ्यते)</em> and that the other manuscripts he examined read “twelve-year-old” (<em>इतीतरेषु हस्तलिखितपुस्तकेषु</em>). The palm leaf manuscript he refers to is MS Kathmandu NAK 5-333 (siglum H), and it does indeed read <em>षोडशवर्षाम्</em> “sixteen” (scribal folio 197r, line 2, image dscn3174 fol196.jpg ).</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/website/assets/img/sodasavarsampatnim-480.webp 480w,/website/assets/img/sodasavarsampatnim-800.webp 800w,/website/assets/img/sodasavarsampatnim-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/website/assets/img/sodasavarsampatnim.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="MS Kathmandu NAK 5-333, scribal folio 197r, line 2." loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>(As a footnote to a footnote, Ācārya made a typo in his 1938 edition: he printed <em>ṣoḍaṣadaśavarṣāṃ</em>; that this was just a typo is proven by his footnote, where he says “ṣoḍaśavarṣāṃ” <a class="citation" href="#susr-1938">(Ācārya &amp; Ācārya, 1938, p. 392)</a>.)</p> <p>The small details of philology and textual criticism can make a large difference to the meaning of a text that has real social impact both for our understanding of the past and for custom in India today. Child marriage is still prevalent in India, although its frequency has been declining since the 1981 census due to modernisation, legal and political action and social activism.</p> <h3 id="references">References</h3> <ol class="bibliography"><li><div class="row"> <div id="chak-2018a" class="col-sm-10"> <div class="title"><em>Jādavjī Trikamjī Ācārya</em></div> <div class="author"> Deepro Chakraborty </div> <div class="periodical"> <em></em> 2018 </div> <div class="periodical"> </div> <div class="links"> <a href="http://n2t.net/ark:/13960/t8z97s417" class="btn btn-sm z-depth-0" role="button">URL</a> </div> </div> </div> </li> <li><div class="row"> <div id="wuja-2023" class="col-sm-10"> <div class="title"><em>On the Plastic Surgery of the Ears and Nose. The Nepalese Version of the Suśrutasaṃhitā</em></div> <div class="author"> <em>Dominik Wujastyk</em>, Jason Birch, Andrey Klebanov, and <span class="more-authors" title="click to view 6 more authors" onclick=" var element=$(this); element.attr('title', ''); var more_authors_text=element.text() == '6 more authors' ? 'Madhu K. Parameswaran, Madhusudan Rimal, Deepro Chakraborty, Harshal Bhatt, Vandana Lele, Paras Mehta' : '6 more authors'; var cursorPosition=0; var textAdder=setInterval(function(){ element.html(more_authors_text.substring(0, cursorPosition + 1)); if (++cursorPosition == more_authors_text.length){ clearInterval(textAdder); } }, '10'); ">6 more authors</span> </div> <div class="periodical"> 2023 </div> <div class="periodical"> </div> <div class="links"> <a href="https://doi.org/10.11588/hasp.1203" class="btn btn-sm z-depth-0" role="button">DOI</a> <a href="/website/assets/pdf/2023_On_the_Plastic_Surgery_of_the_Ears_and_Nose._the_Nepalese_Version_of_the_Su%C5%9Brutasa%E1%B9%83hit%C4%81.pdf" class="btn btn-sm z-depth-0" role="button">PDF</a> </div> </div> </div> </li> <li><div class="row"> <div id="susr-1915" class="col-sm-10"> <div class="title"><em>सुश्रुतसंहिता, सुश्रुतेन विरचिता, वैद्यवरश्रीडल्हणाचार्यविरचितया निबन्धसंग्रहाख्यव्याख्यया समुल्लसिता, आचार्योपाह्वेन त्रिविक्रमात्मजेन यादवशर्मणा संशोधिता = The Sushrutasamhita of Sushruta, the Nibandhasangraha Commentary of Shri Dalhaṇāchārya</em></div> <div class="author"> Yādavaśarma Trivikrama Ācārya </div> <div class="periodical"> 1915 </div> <div class="periodical"> </div> <div class="links"> <a href="http://ark.archive.org/ark:/13960/t3sv0mt50" class="btn btn-sm z-depth-0" role="button">URL</a> </div> </div> </div> </li> <li><div class="row"> <div id="susr-1931" class="col-sm-10"> <div class="title"><em>सुश्रुतसंहिता, वैद्यवरश्रीडल्हणाचार्यविरचितया निबन्धसंग्रहाख्यव्याख्यया समुल्लसिता, महर्षिणा सुश्रुतेन विरचिता, सूत्र-निदान-शारीर-चिकित्सा-कल्पस्थानोत्तरतन्त्रात्मकः = The Sushrutasaṃhitā of Sushruta with the Nibandhasangraha Commentary of Shree Dalhaṇāchārya</em></div> <div class="author"> Yādavaśarma Trivikrama Ācārya </div> <div class="periodical"> 1931 </div> <div class="periodical"> </div> <div class="links"> <a href="http://ark.archive.org/ark:/13960/t9j41sg94" class="btn btn-sm z-depth-0" role="button">URL</a> </div> </div> </div> </li> <li><div class="row"> <div id="susr-1938" class="col-sm-10"> <div class="title"><em>श्रीडल्हणाचार्यविरचितया निबन्धसंग्रहाख्यव्याख्यया निदानस्थानस्य श्रीगयदासाचार्यविरचितया न्यायचन्द्रिकाख्यपञ्जिकाव्याख्यया च समुल्लसिता महर्षिणा सुश्रुतेन विरचिता सुश्रुतसंहिता</em></div> <div class="author"> Yādavaśarma Trivikrama Ācārya and Nārāyaṇa Rāma Ācārya </div> <div class="periodical"> 1938 </div> <div class="periodical"> </div> <div class="links"> <a href="http://ark.archive.org/ark:/13960/s20j9338vs3" class="btn btn-sm z-depth-0" role="button">URL</a> </div> </div> </div> </li></ol>]]></content><author><name>Dominik Wujastyk</name></author><category term="variant_readings"/><category term="marriage"/><category term="textual_analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Society Through Philology]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Textual cruxes</title><link href="https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/cruxes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Textual cruxes"/><published>2025-08-14T15:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-14T15:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/cruxes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/cruxes/"><![CDATA[<p>The project is starting to acquire a significant number of copies of manuscripts of the <em>Śuśrutasaṃhitā</em> (SS). Currently (August 2025), we have manuscripts from Bikaner, Calcutta, Cambridge, Chandigarh, Delhi, Hyderabad, Jamnagar, Jodhpur, Kathmandu, Kurukshetra, Lahore, London, Lucknow and Pune. We don’t have <em>all</em> the manuscripts from each of these places, and all the manuscripts are partial. But the archive is growing.</p> <p>We need to develop techniques for triaging these manuscripts. That is to say, we are aware of a major cleavage in the history of transmission of the SS, between the Nepalese version and the vulgate. So when we look at a new manuscript, we want to have a rapid way of detecting whether it belongs to one or other of these transmissions, or to another transmission that is different from either.</p> <p>At first, I thought the absence of the “<em>yathovāca bhagavān dhanvantariḥ</em>” phrase would be a marker of the Nepalese version. But this is not the case. Manuscripts without this phrase still have vulgate readings. That suggests that the Dhanvantari phrase was added after the vulgate branch had already separated from the Nepalese transmission. We need to look more deeply.</p> <p>One area for research is the passages called <em>pratisaṃskartṛsūtras</em> or “sūtras by revisers” by commentators <a class="citation" href="#meul-hist">(Meulenbeld, 1999, pp. IA 347)</a>. These are passages connected with the comments by Cakrapāṇidatta and – following him – Ḍalhaṇa on the very beginning of the <em>Suśrutasaṃhitā</em> in which they discuss the idea of an older text being later expanded. Cakra and Ḍalhaṇa thought that the use of the perfect tense (Sanskrit <em>liṭ</em>) was a marker of such added passages, for example SS 1.1.1–2, 1.2.1–2, etc. Meulenbeld provided further detail <a class="citation" href="#meul-hist">(<i>A History of Indian Medical Literature</i>, 1999, pp. IIB 444, note 293)</a>.</p> <p>Therefore we want to develop a series of cruxes, that is to say bold, clear diagnostic differences between the Nepalese and the vulgate transmissions. We want to gather a list of these cruxes covering each sthāna, and perhaps several adhyāyas. This blog post will gather such passages.</p> <h2 id="list-of-cruxes">List of cruxes</h2> <p>Sūtrasthāna, adhyāyas 45 and 46 have many verses in the vulgate that do not appear in the Nepalese version, and vice versa. Cruxes in other sthānas too are listed below. Some of the more obvious differences are as follow. This is not an exhaustive list of such differences, just some of the longer, very clear cruxes where large numbers of passages differ.</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th>vulgate numbering</th> <th>in vulgate</th> <th>in Nepalese</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.16.11-14</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.16.26.1-19</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.10.4 (ity eke … na samyak phrase)</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.45.13-16</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>after 1.45.40 4 verses</td> <td>N</td> <td>Y</td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.45.31-42</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.45.66-83</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.45.85-88</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.45.97-107</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.45.116–119</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.45.124-130</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.45.133-142</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.45.145-147</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.45.149-155</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.45.175-181</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.46.210, the following 15 verses</td> <td>N</td> <td>Y</td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.46.250-256</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.46.282-288</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.46.297-312</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.46.326-330</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.46.522-</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>2.1.64-68</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>3.2.10.add1-add11</td> <td>N</td> <td>Y</td> </tr> <tr> <td>3.2.30</td> <td> </td> <td>MS H has a saut du même au même</td> </tr> <tr> <td>3.2.29-31</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>3.2.35.1 - 3.2.35.4</td> <td>N</td> <td>Y</td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>5.1.5cd-6ab (viṣakanyā)</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <h2 id="references">References</h2> <ol class="bibliography"><li><div class="row"> <div id="meul-hist" class="col-sm-10"> <div class="title"><em>A History of Indian Medical Literature</em></div> <div class="author"> Gerrit Jan Meulenbeld </div> <div class="periodical"> 1999 </div> <div class="periodical"> </div> <div class="links"> </div> </div> </div> </li></ol>]]></content><author><name>Dominik Wujastyk</name></author><category term="manuscripts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[cruxes]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Acquiring manuscript images</title><link href="https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/acquiring-manuscript-images/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Acquiring manuscript images"/><published>2025-06-27T07:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-27T07:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/acquiring-manuscript-images</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/acquiring-manuscript-images/"><![CDATA[<p>Work has begun in earnest on the task of collecting more digital copies of manuscripts of the <em>Suśrutasaṃhitā</em>. Currently, the project is seeking copies of manuscripts from the following institutions:</p> <ul> <li>The Asiatic Society of Bengal, in Kolkata,</li> <li>The Calcutta Sanskrit College and University, in Kolkata,</li> <li>The Saraswati Bhavan Library, Vārāṇasī,</li> <li>The Nāgarī Prachārinī Sabhā, Vārāṇasī,</li> <li>The Vārāṇasī Sanskrit College Library (probably an obsolete reference).</li> </ul> <p>There are descriptive entries for the manuscripts at each of these institutions at <a href="https://panditproject.org/entity/42004/work">PanditProject</a> (under “manuscripts”). These listing were updated yesterday with new individual entries for several manuscripts at the Calcutta Sanskrit College that had formerly been grouped in single entries.</p> <h2 id="references">References</h2> <ul> <li>Bandury, Dalia, and Brahmananda Gupta. 2006-2010. “A Descriptive Catalogue of Sanskrit Manuscripts in the Collection of the Asiatic Society. Volume XV - Āyurvedic Manuscripts.” Kolkata: Asiatic Society. 2v.</li> <li>Pandey, Sudhakar. 1973-1978 <em>Nagari Pracarini SabhaHastalikhita Saṃskṛta-grantha-sūci</em>. Varanasi: Nagari Pracarini Sabha, 5 v.</li> <li>Sastri, Hrishikesh, and Siva Chandra Gui. 1895. <em>A Descriptive Catalogue of Sanskrit Manuscripts in the Library of Calcutta Sanskrit College</em>. Calcutta: Baptist Mission Press. volume 10.1 “Medicine.”</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name>Dominik Wujastyk</name></author><category term="manuscripts"/><category term="Suśruta"/><category term="links"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[manuscript copies]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Promotional video for the project (AI generated)</title><link href="https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/promotional-video/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Promotional video for the project (AI generated)"/><published>2025-05-04T14:24:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-04T14:24:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/promotional-video</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/promotional-video/"><![CDATA[<p>Click <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/scl/fi/cudhqoiyk2t0xha1gpj7n/The-Su-ruta-Project-Creatify-video.mp4?rlkey=14046gs52qpv3mjkjx50wmumk&amp;dl=0">here</a> to view video.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Suśruta"/><category term="links"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[promotional video]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Intertextuality and the Methods of Diagnosis</title><link href="https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/intertextuality-full/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Intertextuality and the Methods of Diagnosis"/><published>2025-02-25T14:24:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-25T14:24:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/intertextuality-full</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/intertextuality-full/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="entering-the-road-of-medicine">“Entering the road” of medicine</h3> <p>In the standard, printed edition or vulgate text of the <em>Suśrutasaṃhitā</em>, chapter ten of the Sūtrasthāna is dedicated to the topic of becoming a professional physician (Ācārya, 1938, 42). The title of the chapter is interesting: “how to enter the roadway,” (विशिखानुप्रवेशनीयमध्यायम्). Commentators and dictionaries interpret the word विशिखा to mean “path, road.” (This sense is not common in Sanskrit literature (Meulenbeld, 1999, 1A 351-352; 1B, 323 n102) although it is known to lexicographers and also in Pāli (Vinayapiṭaka, Jātaka) and in Sinhalese (Turner, 1966, #11937). See also SS 3.10.9 for <em>viśikhāntaram</em> “interior of the road,” i.e., vaginal passage. The lexeme <em>śikhā</em> is a loan word in Sanskrit (Lubotsky, 2001, 305).)</p> <h3 id="methods-of-diagnosis">Methods of diagnosis</h3> <p>The fourth passage of the chapter, describes how a physician takes note of omens on the way to a patient’s home, and then how he diagnoses the patient:</p> <blockquote> <p>Then he should approach the house of the sick person according to the favourableness of the messenger, the reason given, omens, and good-luck signs. After sitting down, he should have a good look at the sick person, he should palpate them and interrogate them. Diseases are mostly understandable through these three means of gaining knowledge. That is what some people say, but it is not correct. There are six means of gaining knowledge about diseases, i.e., by the five senses, hearing etc., and by interrogation.</p> </blockquote> <blockquote> <p>दूतनिमित्तशकुनमङ्गलानुलोम्येनातुरगृहमभिगम्य, उपविश्य, आतुरमभिपश्येत्स्पृशेत्पृच्छेच्च; त्रिभिरेतैर्विज्ञानोपायै रोगाः प्रायशो वेदितव्या इत्येके; तत्तु न सम्यक्, षड्विधो हि रोगाणां विज्ञानोपायः, तद्यथा — पञ्चभिः श्रोत्रादिभिः प्रश्नेन चेति ।। ४ ।।| — (Ācārya, 1938, 43)</p> </blockquote> <p>As we see, the text first proposes a three-part method of diagnosis and then immediately distances itself from that statement and provides a different six-part procedure. One has the sense of hearing two voices.</p> <p>Who were the “some people” being referred to? The three-part diagnostic procedure is found in the <em>Carakasaṃhitā</em> (Ca.ci.25.22 (Ācārya, 1938, 592)) . For that reason, this passage has been taken as evidence that the authors of the Suśrutasaṃhitā knew the <em>Carakasaṃhitā</em> and were responding to it (Meulenbeld, 1999, 1A351-352). This is one of the pieces of evidence that is used to argue that the Suśrutasaṃhitā is chronologically later than the <em>Carakasaṃhitā</em>.</p> <p>In the Nepalese version of the <em>Suśrutasaṃhitā</em>, however, the passage is much simpler and omits this second, distancing, voice:</p> <blockquote> <p>Then, arriving at the house of the sick person according to the favourableness of the messenger, the reason given, omens, and good-luck signs, he should sit down. Then, he should have a good look at the sick person, he should palpate them and interrogate them. Through these three means of gaining knowledge it can be known whether life will be long or life will be short.</p> </blockquote> <blockquote> <p>ततो दूतनिमित्तशकुनमङ्गलानुलोम्येनातुरगृहमागम्योपविश्यातुरमभिपश्येत्स्पृशेच्च त्रिभिरेतैर्विज्ञानोपायैः दीर्घमायुषोल्पायुषो वेदितव्यः।</p> </blockquote> <p>Thus, the passage referring to the <em>Carakasaṃhitā</em> is absent.</p> <p>Luckily, for this part of the <em>Suśrutasaṃhitā</em>, the learned commentary of Cakrapāṇidatta (fl. 1075) survives. It was edited and published in 1939 by Yādavaśarman T. Ācārya. Commenting on the passage, Ācārya stated that this extra passage was not known to Cakrapāṇidatta (Ācārya &amp; Śarman, 1939, 77, n.2: अयं पाठश्च चक्रासंगतः). Thus, we can say that it was added to the text of the <em>Suśrutasaṃhitā</em> some time between the oldest Nepalese manuscript (878 CE) and Cakrapāṇidatta’s time, i.e., the eleventh century.</p> <p>The fact that this reference to the <em>Carakasaṃhitā</em> is not present in the early Nepalese version of the <em>Suśrutasaṃhitā</em> means that this argument about the <em>Carakasaṃhitā‘s</em> chronological priority cannot be sustained.</p> <h3 id="references">References</h3> <ul> <li>Ācārya, Yādavaśarman Trivikrama, ed. 1938. <em>सुश्रुतसंहिता, सुश्रुतेन विरचिता, वैद्यवरश्रीडल्हणाचार्यविरचितया निबन्धसंग्रहाख्यव्याख्यया समुल्लसिता, आचार्योपाह्वेन त्रिविक्रमात्मजेन यादवशर्मणा संशोधिता</em>. 3rd ed. Mumbayyāṃ: Nirṇayasāgaramudrāyantrālaye. https://n2t.net/ark:/13960/s20j9338vs3.</li> <li>Ācārya, Yādavaśarman Trivikrama, and Nandakiśora Śarman, eds. 1939. <em>सुश्रुतसंहितायाः सूत्रस्थानम् श्रीचक्रपाणिदत्तविरचितया भानुमतीव्याख्यया समेतम् = Sushrut-Sañhitā (Sūtra Sthān) with Bhānumatī Commentary by Chakrapāṇi Datta with Introduction by Gaṇanāth Sen</em>. Vol. 1. Śrīsvāmi Lakṣmīrāma Nidhi Granthamālā = Shrī Swāmī Lakshmī Rām Trust Series. Agra: Śyāmasundara Śarman.</li> <li>Lubotsky, Alexander. 2001. “The Indo-Iranian Substratum.” In <em>Early Contacts between Uralic and Indo-European: Linguistic and Archaeological Considerations. Papers Presented at an International Symposium Held at the Tvärminne Research Station of the University of Helsinki 8-10 January 1999</em>, edited by Chr Carpelan, Asko Parpola, and P. Koskilallio, 301–17. Helsinki: Suomalais-Ugrilainen Seura. https://www.academia.edu/428961/The_Indo-Iranian_Substratum.</li> <li> <p>Meulenbeld, Gerrit Jan. 1999. <em>A History of Indian Medical Literature</em>. 5 vols. Groningen: E. Forsten.</p> </li> <li>Turner, R. L. 1966. <em>A Comparative Dictionary of the Indo-Aryan Languages</em>. London, New York, Toronto: Oxford University Press. http://dsal.uchicago.edu/dictionaries/soas/.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name>Dominik Wujastyk</name></author><category term="Caraka"/><category term="Suśruta"/><category term="diagnosis"/><category term="textual_analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[on the relationship between the Suśrutasaṃhitā and the Carakasaṃhitā]]></summary></entry></feed>