<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-08-22T04:42:45+00:00</updated><id>https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Compendium of Suśruta in Time and Space</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Social Importance of Variant Readings</title><link href="https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/social-importance-of-variant-readings/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Social Importance of Variant Readings"/><published>2025-08-20T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-20T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/social-importance-of-variant-readings</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/social-importance-of-variant-readings/"><![CDATA[<p>The great scholar Yādavaśarman Trivikrama Ācārya edited three editions of <em>The Compendium of Suśruta</em> (<em>Suśrutasaṃhitā</em>). They were published in 1915, 1931 and 1938. Details of these editions, including the manuscripts Ācārya used, were published in <a class="citation" href="#wuja-2006">(Wujastyk, 2006, chap. 3)</a>.</p> <p>The Suśruta Project has been using an etext transcription of the 1938 edition, typed and generously made public by Tsutomu Yamashita and Yasutaka Muroya in 2014. Because of the limited availability of text editions in Japan at the time, this etext used the 1931 edition for the sūtrasthāna and śārīrasthāna parts of the text. The Suśruta Project 2.0 is currently inputting these parts from the 1938 edition, so that the etext will represent the 1938 edition in a unified way.</p> <p>A side-effect of this work means that we are gaining the possibility of comparing the changes that Ācārya made between his 1931 and 1938 editions. As an example, <a href="https://saktumiva.org/wiki/wujastyk/susrutasamhita/03-su.sa/03-za-vulgate-1931?upama_ver=i4l46viq17">here is the 1931 edition of the <em>Compendium</em> with the apparatus showing the changes that Ācārya made for his 1938 edition</a>.</p> <h2 id="when-should-i-get-married">When should I get married?</h2> <p>If you scroll to passage 10.53 in the śārīrasthāna, where the care of children is being described, you will find a statement advising a young man of 25 years about whom to marry. In the 1915 and 1931 editions, the passage reads :</p> <blockquote> <p>अथास्मै पञ्चविंशतिवर्षाय द्वादशवर्षां पत्नीमावहेत्पित्र्यधर्मार्थकामप्रजाः प्राप्स्यतीति॥</p> <p>Then, a man of twenty-five should take a wife of twelve so that he may obtain children for the sake of ancestral duty, wealth, and pleasure.</p> <p>— Suśrutasaṃhitā Śārīrasthāna 10.53 <a class="citation" href="#susr-1931">(Ācārya, 1931, p. 337)</a></p> </blockquote> <p>But in the 1938 edition, Ācārya emended the passage to read “a wife of sixteen.” Viewed as an important social injunction, this is a major change.</p> <p>In his footnote on this change <a class="citation" href="#susr-1938">(Ācārya &amp; Ācārya, 1938, p. 392)</a>, Ācārya noted that on this point he was adopting the reading of the “palm leaf manuscript” (<em>ṣoḍaśavarṣāṃ iti tā. pustake paṭhyate)</em> and that the other manuscripts he examined read “twelve-year-old” (<em>itītareṣu hastalikhitapustakeṣu</em>). The palm leaf manuscript he refers to is MS Kathmandu NAK 5-333 (siglum H), and it does indeed read <em>ṣoḍaśavarṣām</em> (scribal folio 197r, line 2, image dscn3174 fol196.jpg ).</p> <p>(As a footnote to a footnote, Ācārya made a typo in his 1938 edition: he printed <em>ṣoḍaṣadaśavarṣāṃ</em>; that this was just a typo is proven by his footnote, where he says “ṣoḍaśavarṣāṃ” <a class="citation" href="#susr-1938">(Ācārya &amp; Ācārya, 1938, p. 392)</a>.)</p> <p>The small details of philology and textual criticism can make a large difference to the meaning of a text that - even today - has real social influence.</p> <h3 id="references">References</h3> <ul> <li>Ācārya, Yādavaśarma Trivikrama. 1915. सुश्रुतसंहिता, सुश्रुतेन विरचिता, वैद्यवरश्रीडल्हणाचार्यविरचितया निबन्धसंग्रहाख्यव्याख्यया समुल्लसिता, आचार्योपाह्वेन त्रिविक्रमात्मजेन यादवशर्मणा संशोधिता = the Sushrutasamhita of Sushruta, the Nibandhasangraha Commentary of Shri Dalhaṇāchārya. 1915, Mumbayyāṃ. Nirṇayasāgara Press. http://ark.archive.org/ark:/13960/t3sv0mt50.</li> <li>Ācārya, Yādavaśarman Trivikrama, ed. 1931. <em>सुश्रुतसंहिता, सुश्रुतेन विरचिता, वैद्यवरश्रीडल्हणाचार्यविरचितया निबन्धसंग्रहाख्यव्याख्यया समुल्लसिता, आचार्योपाह्वेन त्रिविक्रमात्मजेन यादवशर्मणा संशोधिता</em>. 2nd ed. Mumbayyāṃ: Nirṇayasāgaramudrāyantrālaye. <a href="https://n2t.net/ark:/13960/t9j41sg94">https://n2t.net/ark:/13960/t9j41sg94</a>.</li> <li>Ācārya, Yādavaśarman Trivikrama, ed. 1938. <em>सुश्रुतसंहिता, सुश्रुतेन विरचिता, वैद्यवरश्रीडल्हणाचार्यविरचितया निबन्धसंग्रहाख्यव्याख्यया समुल्लसिता, आचार्योपाह्वेन त्रिविक्रमात्मजेन यादवशर्मणा संशोधिता</em>. 3rd ed. Mumbayyāṃ: Nirṇayasāgaramudrāyantrālaye. <a href="https://n2t.net/ark:/13960/s20j9338vs3">https://n2t.net/ark:/13960/s20j9338vs3</a>.</li> <li>Chakraborty, Deepro. 2018. “Jādavjī Trikamjī Ācārya.” Unpublished. <a href="http://ark.archive.org/ark:/13960/t8z97s417">http://ark.archive.org/ark:/13960/t8z97s417</a>.</li> <li>Wujastyk, Dominik, Jason Eric Birch, Andrey Klebanov, et al. 2023. *On the Plastic Surgery of the Ears and Nose. The Nepalese Version of the Suśrutasaṃhitā. Heidelberg: Heidelberg Asian Studies Publishing. <a href="https://doi.org/10.11588/hasp.1203">https://doi.org/10.11588/hasp.1203</a>.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name>Dominik Wujastyk</name></author><category term="Suśruta"/><category term="variant"/><category term="readings"/><category term="marriage"/><category term="textual_analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Society Through Philology]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Textual cruxes</title><link href="https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/cruxes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Textual cruxes"/><published>2025-08-14T15:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-14T15:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/cruxes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/cruxes/"><![CDATA[<p>The project is starting to acquire a significant number of copies of manuscripts of the <em>Śuśrutasaṃhitā</em> (SS). Currently (August 2025), we have manuscripts from Bikaner, Calcutta, Cambridge, Chandigarh, Delhi, Hyderabad, Jamnagar, Jodhpur, Kathmandu, Kurukshetra, Lahore, London, Lucknow and Pune. We don’t have <em>all</em> the manuscripts from each of these places, and all the manuscripts are partial. But the archive is growing.</p> <p>We need to develop techniques for triaging these manuscripts. That is to say, we are aware of a major cleavage in the history of transmission of the SS, between the Nepalese version and the vulgate. So when we look at a new manuscript, we want to have a rapid way of detecting whether it belongs to one or other of these transmissions, or to another transmission that is different from either.</p> <p>At first, I thought the absence of the “<em>yathovāca bhagavān dhanvantariḥ</em>” phrase would be a marker of the Nepalese version. But this is not the case. Manuscripts without this phrase still have vulgate readings. That suggests that the Dhanvantari phrase was added after the vulgate branch had already separated from the Nepalese transmission. We need to look more deeply.</p> <p>Therefore we want to develop a series of cruxes, that is to say bold, clear diagnostic differences between the Nepalese and the vulgate transmissions. We want to gather a list of these cruxes covering each sthāna, and perhaps several adhyāyas. This blog post will gather such passages.</p> <h2 id="list-of-cruxes">List of cruxes</h2> <p>Sūtrasthāna, adhyāyas 45 and 46 have many verses in the vulgate that do not appear in the Nepalese version, and vice versa. Cruxes in other sthānas too are listed below. Some of the more obvious differences are as follow. This is not an exhaustive list of such differences, just some of the longer, very clear cruxes where large numbers of passages differ.</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th>vulgate numbering</th> <th>in vulgate</th> <th>in Nepalese</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>1.10.4 (ity eke … na samyak phrase)</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.45.13-16</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>after 1.45.40 4 verses</td> <td>N</td> <td>Y</td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.45.31-42</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.45.66-83</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.45.85-88</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.45.97-107</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.45.116–119</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.45.124-130</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.45.133-142</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.45.145-147</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.45.149-155</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.45.175-181</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.46.210, the following 15 verses</td> <td>N</td> <td>Y</td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.46.250-256</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.46.282-288</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.46.297-312</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.46.326-330</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>1.46.522-</td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>3.2.10.add1-add11</td> <td>N</td> <td>Y</td> </tr> <tr> <td>3.2.30</td> <td> </td> <td>MS H has a saut du même au même</td> </tr> <tr> <td>3.2.29-31</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>3.2.35.1 - 3.2.35.4</td> <td>N</td> <td>Y</td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> <tr> <td>5.1.5cd-6ab (viṣakanyā)</td> <td>Y</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td> </td> <td> </td> <td> </td> </tr> </tbody> </table>]]></content><author><name>Dominik Wujastyk</name></author><category term="Suśruta"/><category term="manuscripts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[cruxes]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Acquiring manuscript images</title><link href="https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/acquiring-manuscript-images/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Acquiring manuscript images"/><published>2025-06-27T07:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-27T07:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/acquiring-manuscript-images</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/acquiring-manuscript-images/"><![CDATA[<p>Work has begun in earnest on the task of collecting more digital copies of manuscripts of the <em>Suśrutasaṃhitā</em>. Currently, the project is seeking copies of manuscripts from the following institutions:</p> <ul> <li>The Asiatic Society of Bengal, in Kolkata,</li> <li>The Calcutta Sanskrit College and University, in Kolkata,</li> <li>The Saraswati Bhavan Library, Vārāṇasī,</li> <li>The Nāgarī Prachārinī Sabhā, Vārāṇasī,</li> <li>The Vārāṇasī Sanskrit College Library (probably an obsolete reference).</li> </ul> <p>There are descriptive entries for the manuscripts at each of these institutions at <a href="https://panditproject.org/entity/42004/work">PanditProject</a> (under “manuscripts”). These listing were updated yesterday with new individual entries for several manuscripts at the Calcutta Sanskrit College that had formerly been grouped in single entries.</p> <h2 id="references">References</h2> <ul> <li>Bandury, Dalia, and Brahmananda Gupta. 2006-2010. “A Descriptive Catalogue of Sanskrit Manuscripts in the Collection of the Asiatic Society. Volume XV - Āyurvedic Manuscripts.” Kolkata: Asiatic Society. 2v.</li> <li>Pandey, Sudhakar. 1973-1978 <em>Nagari Pracarini SabhaHastalikhita Saṃskṛta-grantha-sūci</em>. Varanasi: Nagari Pracarini Sabha, 5 v.</li> <li>Sastri, Hrishikesh, and Siva Chandra Gui. 1895. <em>A Descriptive Catalogue of Sanskrit Manuscripts in the Library of Calcutta Sanskrit College</em>. Calcutta: Baptist Mission Press. volume 10.1 “Medicine.”</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name>Dominik Wujastyk</name></author><category term="Suśruta"/><category term="links"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[manuscript copies]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Promotional video for the project (AI generated)</title><link href="https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/promotional-video/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Promotional video for the project (AI generated)"/><published>2025-05-04T14:24:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-04T14:24:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/promotional-video</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/promotional-video/"><![CDATA[<p>Click <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/scl/fi/cudhqoiyk2t0xha1gpj7n/The-Su-ruta-Project-Creatify-video.mp4?rlkey=14046gs52qpv3mjkjx50wmumk&amp;dl=0">here</a> to view video.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Suśruta"/><category term="links"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[promotional video]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Intertextuality and the Methods of Diagnosis</title><link href="https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/intertextuality-full/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Intertextuality and the Methods of Diagnosis"/><published>2025-02-25T14:24:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-25T14:24:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/intertextuality-full</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sushrutaproject2.github.io/website/blog/2025/intertextuality-full/"><![CDATA[<p>In the standard, printed edition or vulgate text of the <em>Suśrutasaṃhitā</em>, chapter ten of the Sūtrasthāna is dedicated to the topic of becoming a professional physician (Ācārya, 1938, 42). The title of the chapter is interesting: “how to enter the roadway,” (विशिखानुप्रवेशनीयमध्यायम्). Commentators and dictionaries interpret the word विशिखा to mean “path, road.” (This sense is not common in Sanskrit literature (Meulenbeld, 1999, 1A 351-352; 1B, 323 n102) although it is known to lexicographers and also in Pāli (Vinayapiṭaka, Jātaka) and in Sinhalese (Turner, 1966, #11937). See also SS 3.10.9 for <em>viśikhāntaram</em> “interior of the road,” i.e., vaginal passage. The lexeme <em>śikhā</em> is a loan word in Sanskrit (Lubotsky, 2001, 305).)</p> <p>The fourth passage of the chapter, describes how a physician takes note of omens on the way to a patient’s home, and then how he diagnoses the patient:</p> <blockquote> <p>Then he should approach the house of the sick person according to the favourableness of the messenger, the reason given, omens, and good-luck signs. After sitting down, he should have a good look at the sick person, he should palpate them and interrogate them. Diseases are mostly understandable through these three means of gaining knowledge. That is what some people say, but it is not correct. There are six means of gaining knowledge about diseases, i.e., by the five senses, hearing etc., and by interrogation.</p> </blockquote> <blockquote> <p>दूतनिमित्तशकुनमङ्गलानुलोम्येनातुरगृहमभिगम्य, उपविश्य, आतुरमभिपश्येत्स्पृशेत्पृच्छेच्च; त्रिभिरेतैर्विज्ञानोपायै रोगाः प्रायशो वेदितव्या इत्येके; तत्तु न सम्यक्, षड्विधो हि रोगाणां विज्ञानोपायः, तद्यथा — पञ्चभिः श्रोत्रादिभिः प्रश्नेन चेति ।। ४ ।।| — (Ācārya, 1938, 43)</p> </blockquote> <p>As we see, the text first proposes a three-part method of diagnosis and then immediately distances itself from that statement and provides a different six-part procedure. One has the sense of hearing two voices.</p> <p>Who were the “some people” being referred to? The three-part diagnostic procedure is found in the <em>Carakasaṃhitā</em> (Ca.ci.25.22 (Ācārya, 1938, 592)) . For that reason, this passage has been taken as evidence that the authors of the Suśrutasaṃhitā knew the <em>Carakasaṃhitā</em> and were responding to it (Meulenbeld, 1999, 1A351-352). This is one of the pieces of evidence that is used to argue that the Suśrutasaṃhitā is chronologically later than the <em>Carakasaṃhitā</em>.</p> <p>In the Nepalese version of the <em>Suśrutasaṃhitā</em>, however, the passage is much simpler and omits this second, distancing, voice:</p> <blockquote> <p>Then, arriving at the house of the sick person according to the favourableness of the messenger, the reason given, omens, and good-luck signs, he should sit down. Then, he should have a good look at the sick person, he should palpate them and interrogate them. Through these three means of gaining knowledge it can be known whether life will be long or life will be short.</p> </blockquote> <blockquote> <p>ततो दूतनिमित्तशकुनमङ्गलानुलोम्येनातुरगृहमागम्योपविश्यातुरमभिपश्येत्स्पृशेच्च त्रिभिरेतैर्विज्ञानोपायैः दीर्घमायुषोल्पायुषो वेदितव्यः।</p> </blockquote> <p>Thus, the passage referring to the <em>Carakasaṃhitā</em> is absent.</p> <p>Luckily, for this part of the <em>Suśrutasaṃhitā</em>, the learned commentary of Cakrapāṇidatta (fl. 1075) survives. It was edited and published in 1939 by Yādavaśarman T. Ācārya. Commenting on the passage, Ācārya stated that this extra passage was not known to Cakrapāṇidatta (Ācārya &amp; Śarman, 1939, 77, n.2: अयं पाठश्च चक्रासंगतः). Thus, we can say that it was added to the text of the <em>Suśrutasaṃhitā</em> some time between the oldest Nepalese manuscript (878 CE) and Cakrapāṇidatta’s time, i.e., the eleventh century.</p> <p>The fact that this reference to the <em>Carakasaṃhitā</em> is not present in the early Nepalese version of the <em>Suśrutasaṃhitā</em> means that this argument about the <em>Carakasaṃhitā‘s</em> chronological priority cannot be sustained.</p> <h3 id="references">References</h3> <ul> <li>Ācārya, Yādavaśarman Trivikrama, ed. 1938. <em>सुश्रुतसंहिता, सुश्रुतेन विरचिता, वैद्यवरश्रीडल्हणाचार्यविरचितया निबन्धसंग्रहाख्यव्याख्यया समुल्लसिता, आचार्योपाह्वेन त्रिविक्रमात्मजेन यादवशर्मणा संशोधिता</em>. 3rd ed. Mumbayyāṃ: Nirṇayasāgaramudrāyantrālaye. https://n2t.net/ark:/13960/s20j9338vs3.</li> <li>Ācārya, Yādavaśarman Trivikrama, and Nandakiśora Śarman, eds. 1939. <em>सुश्रुतसंहितायाः सूत्रस्थानम् श्रीचक्रपाणिदत्तविरचितया भानुमतीव्याख्यया समेतम् = Sushrut-Sañhitā (Sūtra Sthān) with Bhānumatī Commentary by Chakrapāṇi Datta with Introduction by Gaṇanāth Sen</em>. Vol. 1. Śrīsvāmi Lakṣmīrāma Nidhi Granthamālā = Shrī Swāmī Lakshmī Rām Trust Series. Agra: Śyāmasundara Śarman.</li> <li>Lubotsky, Alexander. 2001. “The Indo-Iranian Substratum.” In <em>Early Contacts between Uralic and Indo-European: Linguistic and Archaeological Considerations. Papers Presented at an International Symposium Held at the Tvärminne Research Station of the University of Helsinki 8-10 January 1999</em>, edited by Chr Carpelan, Asko Parpola, and P. Koskilallio, 301–17. Helsinki: Suomalais-Ugrilainen Seura. https://www.academia.edu/428961/The_Indo-Iranian_Substratum.</li> <li> <p>Meulenbeld, Gerrit Jan. 1999. <em>A History of Indian Medical Literature</em>. 5 vols. Groningen: E. Forsten.</p> </li> <li>Turner, R. L. 1966. <em>A Comparative Dictionary of the Indo-Aryan Languages</em>. London, New York, Toronto: Oxford University Press. http://dsal.uchicago.edu/dictionaries/soas/.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name>Dominik Wujastyk</name></author><category term="Caraka"/><category term="Suśruta"/><category term="diagnosis"/><category term="textual_analysis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[on the relationship between the Suśrutasaṃhitā and the Carakasaṃhitā]]></summary></entry></feed>